[Applause]
one two one two can everyone hear me
okay okay thank you very much Angela
bakar and uh Marina um and thank you
obviously to the University of Cambridge
for uh agreeing to put this on I'm
roinet I'm a therapist I've also as well
worked in higher education for over 25
years at the University of grenage
university of s University of theas
London and most LLY at the University of
Oxford in student support roles rather
than as academic I devised this Blackman
on the couch about 12 years ago 12 years
ago 22 years ago now actually I'm
getting old um after I um completed my
masters and found that black men were
not accessing University counseling
services so I thought why not put on a
product like this and invite them to
events like this to hear stories like
from our guests today that might Inspire
them to seek support as and when
needed um without further Ado let's just
get on given that we we're running late
uh so my very first guest is um Lord
Simon wooy now Simon woly even before
today you're very much an inspiration to
many people outside the university and
of course within the university um I
came across you during um your work in
um operation black vote um and I
remember when you first wrote your book
you went to Beacon Bookshop in North
London and you you went there to go and
do a book signing and my sister lives
just around the corner from there and I
rang up very quickly and says look Lord
Willie's just over there please go over
there get a book get him to sign it and
so she did Julie as a little sister
normally does when I ask her to do
things and this is the book and
thankfully um Lord Willie you you signed
uh you signed in here and my sister did
say to you look my brother he's running
this thing called Blackwood on the couch
would you be interested in a in
attending you said yes straight away
which is fantastic because normally what
happens is and I've written to virtually
every single black male celebrity in
this country and ask them if they're
willing to s seriously if they're
willing to to attend and the vast
majority of them are like good idea nope
but Lord Willie said yes straight away
so here we are so many uh months later
so thank you very much for that now
normally and when I first devised this I
did want to try and have counseling
sessions on stage but that's virtually
impossible because they are normally
private um private um um matters but
what we will do is we'll have a
discussion there'll be some counseling
type questions of course things won't be
confidential because well we've got
people here and listening across the
world hopefully um so you know we'll
just we'll just have a a conversation
what I tend to do is I I'll ask one
pre-planned question and then we'll go
um and have conversations from there the
planned question I'd like to ask you
first if I may is um you've shared some
of your challenges relating to diversity
and inclusion in your book saw and it's
obvious that leading a prestigious
institution like homon college and also
being a member of House of Lords must
come with unique challenges and opport
opportunities can you share some of your
experiences in addressing diversity and
inclusion within those settings and how
these efforts are impacted on your own
uh mental health and the well-being of
black men in Academia and in political
settings sorry longwinded but I hope you
got all of that it's okay it's okay so
over to you I first want to say thank
you to you but by the way can you can
you hear me can you hear me on
online
yeah this side
is that better that's better that's
better I want to praise you first and
foremost um I've spent 30 years being an
activist um believing that I can get
things done believing I can make a
difference along along with others and I
want to pay tribute to you for for
bringing this to us I me it's your idea
but you took that idea and and made it
happen and so when you're sister said to
me you know would I would I do this of
course I want to say yes because I
recognize a fellow activist that that
has the
audacity if you like to believe that
they can make a difference that not only
benefits people like you and me that
look like you and me but why the society
no thank you for that um but to to your
to your question I think that having
that audacity the that that that
self-belief and Collective belief it's
not arrogance but it's this belief that
that you have a purpose to to do to do
good things hopefully great things but
you you don't know um that if you are
doing things that that change structural
inequalities then you're always going to
be in difficult
terrain and sometimes very difficult
terrain and uh spending 30 years with
with operation black vote tackling
tackling systemic racism by the way we
started operation black vote in
1996 uh maybe some of you here weren't
even
born but but we did so we did so because
black men and women were dying in police
custody M and nobody was being held to
account and often we would we would take
to our own streets and tear our own
streets down because we wanted Justice
and we said look we can't be tearing our
streets down we need to understand how
to get systemic change and I remember a
good friend of mine a great colleague of
Mine Derek Hines he said to me Simon
we've got to use The Ballot Box not the
bullet which is a a Malcolm X ref Fran
and so that journey of of challenging
the
police uh challenging uh local
Democratic institutions the Judiciary uh
Westminster I've spent most of my life
people disagreeing with
me I've spent most of my life being gas
lit that you don't have a problem it's
all about Merit take the chip off your
shoulder
um look at that ethnic group if they can
do it why can't
you um and
so it's not new to
me sometimes it's more
disappointing uh often when you see when
you see a rabid racist you you know that
you got to put up your
fists um and but when you see someone
with a smile and say I'm on your
side and yet the outcome is not UND
disimilar
then you have to you one you you're
disappointed and two you have to use
another
tactic and tell me tell me about the
other tactic I mean I like the refrain
you used from uh Malcolm X or or Martin
Luther King about the The Ballot or The
Bullet I automatically think of Malcolm
X standing by the curtains with his
rifle looking through the window and
thinking more about the bullet than the
ballot itself in in in the circumstances
in which you found yourself in and
obviously operation black vote is one
way to deal with the circumstances in
which black people face have you come
across situations where you thought it
would perhaps take a little bit more
than that the Malcolm X approach when
you've been in the House of Lords when
you've been at a place like Cambridge or
or or anywhere else for that matter yeah
I mean sometimes I've had to point the
finger and uh and say
behave sometimes I about to be in in in
somebody's somebody's face um but I do
remember in the House of Lords when
there was a was a moment uh I was
talking there was a debate about um
about uh racism and uh and about um sto
and sech and I saw a member of the House
of Lords
laugh and I said you think it's funny
you should ask child
Q if it's funny to be stopped searched
and humiliated that's a bit about CH she
was stopped and searched uh whil on whil
menstruating
and uh i' I'd begun the debate because I
feel that I feel that I have to um speak
truth to power and not be afraid of that
so I'm in this gilded chamber the House
of Lords is utterly gilded with gold
there's a throne where the king sits
when he opens
Parliament and um I feel that it's it's
my
duty so we're in this debate and it's my
turn to speak and I said my Lords and
Ladies is hands up if you've been
stopped and
searched I look around and there's
muttering uh hands up if you've been
stopped and stripped
searched and they're looking around and
I could hear one p behind me saying
saying you can't say that you can't do
that I just did it that's a powerful
question I just did it and
so and I'll check how many hands did go
up oh none of course no no no no but it
but it's about it's about saying look
it's it's not about me it's about my
role in these places but here's here's
the other thing I think this is really
important sometimes you have to be
strong physically strong but to get
things
done ultimately you've got to take
people on a journey with you and I I was
really wonderfully fortunate to be on
desert island dis just just recently and
Lauren Le said in her introduction she
said what characterizes uh your your
journey and transformation to to to
these institutions is that it seems to
me that you've adopted conversation
rather than
confrontation and I I often tell uh
black activist other activist um I say
to
them that I I want you to be brilliant I
want you to be to have all the tools in
your Armory but above all I want you to
be
smart when when when I was uh much
younger in the in the political space
I'd be too angry for my own good I'd win
the argument but not taking anyone
forward because I felt that I had the
the moral Authority the
righteousness to demand to be angry but
the shutters came down and I thought
this is not
working I I need to be able to
almost Hold Your
Hand even though you might be my enemy
even though you might be an enemy that
smiles or or or not understanding and
and together we go on a journey in which
I say um if if I win doesn't mean you
lose can I show you a pathway in which I
win you win and we all win and tell me
tell me about the time when you realize
that that was the way the way forward I
mean I do want to get to the question
about how all of this impacts on your
own right mental health but tell me tell
me about when this all hard lessons hard
lessons have just have
just I think and this and it's right
that you bring it back to mental health
because I'd come away from those angry
conversations I mean you know I'd often
ruin dinner parties
uh just you know we're having nice food
here's the other thing too about about
being about being nice about being
polite I'd make people feel so
relaxed that they forget I was
black I swear to you I swear so I give
you an example we're having nice poite
conversation as black people honest
honestly you lean into what that other
person likes you lean into making them
feel comfortable it's what we do I I
call it a hidden
superpower because often we don't even
know we're doing it you're making the
other person feel relaxed but you can
make them feel so relaxed then they can
turn around to you out of the blue and
say what is it with these black kids why
can't they
study to my
face why can't they do well at
school and I'd say say hm no funny
enough actually people thought that
about young women back in the day that
their place was best in the kitchen and
they couldn't go on to education and
then you could
see oh I'm sorry then you know maybe a
few tears
and and or anger back at
me um so it's a it's a Highwire act it's
a Highwire Act
um but and I don't always get it right
but I think you know I'm 60 nearly 62
now um You should say don't look
it you
don't you're fantastic for your AG but
but what are the techniques then that
you use to make non-white people happy
or comfortable yeah I mean is it a case
of walking down the street and crossing
the road when you see somebody coming
towards you who isn't the same color who
isn't the same gender or is there
something else that you're doing I don't
know I don't know I mean I think my my
mother who um who brought me up as white
uh by the way and um she wait wait a
minute what do you mean by that your
your mother brought you up as white no
no no no but no I was fostered then
adopted by my parents yes she she showed
me lots of love lots of love she chose
me and so I think I hope I do I do just
want to stop you there but because sorry
for interrupting you before by saying
that but normally you know in counseling
and Psychotherapy if there's a Freud and
slip of some sort it normally comes from
somewhere and the fact that I thought I
heard you say that you're mother brought
you up white was saying something that
might be what you wanted to hear
maybe and it also as well actually may
Bebe coming from where you I mean I am
on the
couch but but sorry I was given lots of
love and and so it's easy I hope it's
easy for me to show love and I think if
you show love and you show decency um
then people are more likely to warm to
you and if if then you can have the
difficult
conversations then it's a
win-win um and you know I feel blessed
in this job I have a I have the greatest
job uh because because I mean there's
one thing to transform institutions
there's quite another to
educate and uh I I feel that I'm not
only and I don't mean this in a big eded
way at all but I I often feel that I'm
not only educating 1,400
students uh but uh I'm on a journey of
education
for my our institution and more broadly
Cambridge and then when you think about
Cambridge one of the most elite
institutions
on the planet if if Cambridge can get it
better
uh uh nearly
right then that's a beacon well what I'd
like you to think about also as well as
the in some ways adjust the position of
you here in Cambridge and you in your
white family right I mean in some ways
it's very interesting that you've ended
up here and are able to manage in the
way that you have right because I think
you're partly saying also as well that
being adopted by a white family has in
some ways prepared you for majority
white situations are you saying that is
there anything about that that rings a
bell yeah I think a lot of a lot of kids
in the 1970s we went to all white
schools but but you know when in the
1970s at
school you very quickly you were very
quickly aware that you were black and
you very quickly aware that you wanted
to be black I mean not just because of
Pelle or or or Muhammad Ali but um you
knew the system was against us I mean
don't get me wrong a lot of us black
kids in Wy
schools uh wanted to be like the white
kids uh particularly the ones with blue
blond hair and blue eyes because you
know the one they got all the girls and
and
uh as a kid you want to
belong but we quickly dawned on us that
we couldn't belong so we had to be us so
we had to be the Pelle you had to be the
Muhammad Ali and and own and own that uh
if you like because that gave us status
it gave us Pride but we had to navigate
through this white world and I yes
you're right I've been I've been doing
that and I've had to learn and I know
this I'm on the couch I might as well
say it um I've had to learn to own my
blackness uh tell me a bit more about
that what do you mean well I I think
because you want to be long that you try
and particularly in the white spaces fit
in um you want to wear the clothes you
you you uh I don't get me wrong I never
listen to rock
music trust me
what music do you listen to uh Jazz um
dance music um but but but you know in
saying that I found regged initially
difficult because I wasn't in that black
space I wasn't in that Caribbean space
that listen to that listen to Bob Marley
you know I love Bob Marley but I wasn't
I wasn't I wasn't
drenched I wasn't drenched in that now
this is interesting and let me just tell
you about my counter trans reaction when
I hear you you say this because in the
first 10 15 minutes you come across as
somebody who is very good at
acclimatizing to the situation in which
you find yourself in I mean there's a
brilliant example in your book where I
think you were a mechanical engineer in
a garage and there was lots of Asian
guys as well as white guys and you
acclimatized yourself with the Asian
members of the the garage and you became
very close friends with them and you
fitted in you managed to fit in right
you've managed to fit in in many areas
of your life with the majority um around
you sure but yet now we're going to be
talking about a black majority situation
uh you know people who listen to Reg or
who listen to Jazz you said that you
found that a bit more of a challenge did
I hear you right no no no nice
try I know what I what I meant was is
that I wasn't I I wasn't and it wasn't
my daily life and so when I my other
black friends at the time if they lived
in a black family you went into the
house and there was reggy music lots of
regy music and and and so and there are
dreadlocks and and and I
didn't in saying I had to find my
blackness is the truth because if you're
in a White House why would you know
about the origins of of um the Caribbean
and and and and so I I had to learn it I
had to own it and then I had to take it
with me now owning
it uh uh and taking it with
me
um it's been my journey but I also
cannot uh uh dismantle if you like that
uh those white spaces and so to your
point that may have given me some
strings to my bow in which I've been
able to navigate as you said when I was
in Leicester I had the choice when I was
in Leicester as a car mechanic um I went
into this garage as an apprenticeship
and on one side there were white white
uh mechanics on the other side there
were Asian where do I go I well I
actually went with the with the other
white
apprenticeships and uh so I went with
them and and got into trouble got into
trouble very quickly is it gone
again can you hear me yeah got I got
into trouble I crashed the car uh after
like the my sixth week and I didn't even
have a license and um one of the Asian
guys said to me you want to learn this
you want to learn this trade you want to
be a sensible uh young man bring your
bring your um tool kit and and uh come
and join us so I went to the other side
and immersed myself in in um Indian
culture IND Indian food and learn to be
a good car mechanic indeed and as I say
to remind you yes you've been very good
at climatizing into the situations in
which you find yourself and you also as
well mentioned that you had to learn
about Blackness yeah tell me when and
how that happened well I mean you always
know you're black because because when
you were when we were I know S 8 9 10
the skinet would say send the
Ws to Vietnam so you knew you were
targeted uh uh when we played football
and we were fast we were called Pelle
um but these were Snippets of of of
Blackness it wasn't until actually you
had go to The
Barbers me and my brother uh my white
mother didn't know how to do our hair
but somebody said to her go to Highfield
where the black area was and um and
they'll do they'll do your boy's hair
and me and my brother used to go to the
barbers in Highfield which is a black
area and we go to this person's flat and
we'd get there about
10:00 in the morning on a Sunday morning
and we wouldn't leave till
5: cuz if you were a kid you had to wait
you had to wait all the adults would
come in and then they'd get their hair
done and you'd be like
this and you kept
storm and but I learned black politics
in that
Barbers I I heard them men cuss out
black people white people and the and
the the fact that that we had
Independence in the Caribbean but no
power and it just it I just absorbed it
I didn't even know I was absorbing
it uh uh but I think you know when I
come to the making of Simon
woolly being in that Barber's flat for
the for so many hours was instrumental
what was it like for you then at s eight
n years old to realize that there was
something more to you than the previous
seven years eight years well it made you
angry made you
angry and um uh me and my friends very
quickly we we all learned how to
fight okay we all went boxing through a
boxing club because we knew I mean you
know the older guys they knew they told
you about Injustice and they said you
better be you better look after yourself
you better look after yourself so we all
learned how to box my friend Chris pip
went on to become a world
champion um I saw him a couple of weeks
ago uh but I mean we all went to the
boxing uh ring and thought we were
Muhammad Ali just dancing around and I
was I was quick you I look good until
someone hit
me said bam get me out of
here uh but I know how to fight you know
how to you know how to look after look
after myself yeah several examples of
that in your your book as well you did
not have to look after yourself so you
then learned or began to learn that you
were black and that you were different
right um even though you were living in
a majority White household and majority
White City as it was at the time um tell
me about if you remember then what kind
of impact that might have had on your
well-being as well and maybe your mental
health and and what I'm interested in
really is how you've managed
to keep a straight face keep good mental
health keep good well-being when you
have continuous challenges related to
your
to your race I you know what looking
back now I have no idea how we
survived I swear to
you we we fa we faced such
atrocious racism from people who should
have known better who's we uh in schools
okay people in positions of power uh
when you're a young man going for a job
when you're going to the bank I remember
coming to London uh coming to London
from Leicester must have been about 17
18 18 uh and uh I remember going to i'
got a job and I said to the bank Clark
or manager or whatever could I have a
overdraft uh for £100 because of the
timing and I remember look him in the
eyes and and you know when you're black
you know that look you just do you can't
say it but you know it and they look at
you in the eyes and say
no and you want to
scream but no one's
listening you know if you lose
it if you lose
it you'll be behind
bars
and I saw that happen too there was me
and the Chris pie at the Box
his brother Raymond Patt and three other
white friends we're all you know real
mixed working class Council Estate Group
and we're in
town and the white kid Daren Derby plays
with an ATM ATMs had just come about he
plays with an ATM before you know it
three police cars Converge on us all
Raymond P's the tallest play uh
presented England at high jump the
police officers jump out the car and
jump on him first and they're whacking
him and they're whacking
him and he's fighting back fighting back
proud man Roman
P he gets taken away he gets taken away
they charge him listen to this they
charge him with
assault he did nothing he tried to
defend himself they TR and I I saw that
with my own
eyes in fact in fact uh in
court I was a a
witness and I was still at school and
I'm in the dock first time I've been in
court and I'm in the dock and I see all
these people and the prosecutor said to
me so Simon woolly you're a good friend
of Raymond yes I am and you think he's a
good young man yes he
is uh and then he said to me would you
be surprised if Raymond P said to a
police officer copper you
stink and uh and um uh no he said would
you would you say that Raven would say
that and I and I said no and he did he
did the the the prosecutor said are you
surprised I said yes I'm surprised and
the court laughed and and I said but I
tell you
this I tell you one thing for sure that
I saw with my own eyes that we were
minding our own business police officers
came and beat up my friend beat him up I
was this little kid in the in the
dog he was found not
guilty yeah not
surprisingly what sort of impact did
that have on you to see that the police
would be like this with you and your
peers who happen to be the same color
well I mean it's it's a cumulative I
mean I had the same when I came out my
house I came out my house once with a
bag of washing with a bag of washing my
my my uh washing ma uh machine broke
down I come out the house I'm living in
leafy South Woodford I'm a young kid
from Leicester and I'm you know I've got
a I wouldn't say a loud mouth but I can
you know I can talk and I'm a good
salesman anyway so I bought my own I
bought my own uh
flat 22 years of
age I come out the flat I come out the
flat with a bag of washing and I'm
walking down the the street in in South
Woodford and a police car comes
by screeches to a halt Rivers is
up and the police officers jump
out what you doing I said I'm going to
the lingered they said there's been a
spat of burglaries around here I said be
some burglary wouldn't I stealing dirty
washing they said to me have you got any
ID I said I don't need ID to go to the
LA
R I said look I will show you ID this is
this is my car this is my house I went
to go into the house I'm opening the
door and I'm going up the stairs and
then the police officer was behind me
and I turned around to him I'm 22 years
of age I said where you going he said
I'm coming with you I said no you're not
you're not invited you wait here and as
I went to go up the stairs he ran up the
stairs and dragged me down dragged me
down the stairs and arrested me he
chained me to the the Gate of my house
outside the house and said wait here
wait here we'll see if this if you live
here and he knocked on my neighbor's
house uh and my neighbor come out and
said he said is this do you know this
person said yeah that's Simon but now
they're enjoying their power yeah so
they knock on somebody else's house too
they do and I I do want to put the same
question to you again Simon with' Just 5
minutes left to go only because I've had
young men sit in a seat where you're sat
with exactly the same circumstances
going to the laundr back in the day
teenagers being stopped by police
bundled into the back of a van and the
impact on them is that they end up with
agrob and not leaving the house for many
years because they're frightened they're
going to get accosted again that's the
impact it's had on your mental health I
want to ask you again about the
continuous growing number of incidents
that you may have witnessed or at least
you know being a victim of how has that
impacted upon
you the truth is the truth is until
these conversations and I have to hold
the emotion back because I relive it
that the
humiliation I would argue most black
people get a
box put it in the Box
okay put a lock on
it
keep it
closed keep it closed and I tell you I
tell you how I know that because the the
Simon something that you do it is the
Simon wlly today if I'd have been
arrested I'd be suing there
behind the reason why I put it in the
Box why do you
think tell me I need to get on with life
and I cannot carry that that
burden of pain you
cannot will not put it in the Box you
know I say to myself don't get mad get
successful don't get mad get in a
position of power where you can make a
difference I mean I'm sure I'm not
saying that at the time but somebody
some maybe maybe my mother who was pass
now maybe she's maybe she's saying to me
you have a bigger calling bigger calling
the but to your
point black men need
space to have these uh
conversations where they can share the
lived
experience and and not let it
internalize where it can become a a
something quite poisonous if you like a
space Also as one maybe to open the box
correct just a little correct correct if
is there a fear or a worry also as well
for black men or rather about it's
traumatic it's traumatic to open the box
I'm opening it now and I'm I'm uh you
know I'm you know I'm on camera I can't
cry I can't but it's reliving some of
that okay um I I I just wrote an
article uh last week it's published
today about the the uh black Atlantic
the black
Atlantic uh and I think with the
enslavement of
Africans for many black people I
know you know we know about it we know
how it's changed the world we know how
it's we have a a global
inequity but we often choose to keep it
in the box but I chose to open that box
and go to this
exhibition and go to this exhibition and
you know I employ all of you if you have
if you have that strength for that
moment to go it's
traumatic it's it and how do you manage
that trauma I was
angry uh you know is a is a This Global
Museum in which tens of thousands of
people go
to predicated on the enslavement of
Africans that's a tough called I think
they are addressing
that uh but to see it and there's a
there's a wonderful uh gut-wrenching
piece in which um uh alado
aquano um uh comes alive in a actor
who's reading um his um Reflections on
the passage from the old world the
African world to the new world and so
almost from the grave somebody's telling
you what
happened wow wow I'm afraid we're fast
running out of time we're just about to
to say goodbye and there's so much we
can talk about is there um anything
you'd like to leave us with before you
finish you know you know Cambridge
Cambridge University is a is a is a
great institution and for me that it is
going on an extraordinary
Journey um that that
it's open that
box in in terms of in terms of I would
argue some of the biggest questions it's
ever
had ever
had and it's traumatic for them it's
traumatic for
us about who we are yeah who gets H who
gets
elevated uh I I I have these
conversations give the the black
students past present and
future a sense of
belonging not just a place in
which as some might say they
survived but they
thrived they thrived and their
thriving benefits the whole world
absolutely it does hopefully there'll be
an opportunity to maybe raise a little
bit more of this during the question and
answer session but for now thank you so
much Lord Willie for your for your few
moments thank
you take
a okay um our second guest and before
the break is George the poet so if I can
please invite George up on
stage what I've seen them do in some
talk shows is they have a bit of music
in the
background and normally the uh the guest
comes on dancing as well but we're not
going to do that how you doing man see
you please take a
seat okay um as people have already
witnessed and as you know yourself for
sure um this isn't even as long as a
therapeutic hour which normally takes 50
minutes or so um but I suppose the thing
is with me and you this is not the first
time we're meeting thankfully um just
last week we met at the University of L
at the black man on the couch event
there MH and spent half an hour well
basically having a discussion about um
you and your life so in a way this is
perhaps the first time in the whole of
the series while it did happen once
before with Paul Cannonville the first
black player for Chelsea but but the
first time for a while that I've had
someone who's come back for a follow-up
session so thank you very much for doing
that George is a privilege good to see
you again man um what I tend to do when
I meet a client for the second time
is ask them about their experience what
they thought of the first session and
what's been going on for them in the um
seven days since so what did you think
of the first time we met um so in the
first session we had a yeah please we
had a conversation similar to the one
you and salmon just had where uh I talk
a little bit about my personal
experience but it quickly slips into the
international context into the
historical context and you know what I I
actually felt a little bit bad thank you
I felt bad not not bad but self-aware in
doing that because um I tend to be
someone who's immersed in the thought
you know in the in in Reflections on
history and the global context and um
again to Simon's point about being at
polite you know dinner dinner settings
and being the one to take the
conversation a certain direction
especially being a husband now for two
years learning about when and you know
time and a place for different kind of
conversations um I just feel like I I I
would I don't enjoy that that seems to
be my default you know talking about my
life in the context of the historical
black struggle but I I can't help it uh
and I don't know that I'm doing it
certain times I'm just I'm just talking
about my relationship with Blackness my
relationship with um education Africa
the you know black Britain Britain
itself and yeah in doing that you know
it slides that way so sometimes I
reflect on our conversation and I think
what would it have taken for me to not
you know end up talking about that but
um I don't know is counseling a
Psychotherapy is about well I suppose
more than anything else self-awareness
and finding out a bit more about who we
are where we come from why we do the
things we do um and I think I might have
explained to you in the in the first
session that the way I tend to work is
to give some focus and attention to
relationships with significant others
parents and other loved ones um and how
you might replicate or repeat those
patterns of behavior in the in the here
and now and I I wouldn't mind maybe
spending a few moments thinking a little
about your early life um and how that
was and how maybe you might repeat the
patterns of that uh we do know that you
were a a student of the University of
and I would very much like to find out
how you negotiated your your way through
an elite institution like this I know
you were also as well in a private
school but but first things first tell
me a little bit about your your
upbringing um I grew up in Northwest
London my mom my dad and my big brother
um before long my you know four more
little siblings came came along I had a
lot of we had a lot of as me and my
brother as the oldest had a lot of
respons responsibility over our siblings
um but you know we had a good time there
was a lot of music in my house um what
sort of
Music a lot of music
from the kind of from the earth winds
and Fir to the Bal lot of Michael
Jackson my brother and I were obsessed
with Michael Jackson okay but so were my
parents in our
defense and
um yeah um my my older brother quickly
got into rap which did I take it did I
take to rap straight
away yeah I think I did him more so
though and rap became a big like a main
character in our lives and in our
community led to me becoming a rapper
which led to me becoming a poet because
I was in Cambridge the context didn't
feel appropriate to rap but I switched
my style it was the same lyrics but a
different
delivery um
um yeah I don't know what you want to
know
well let's let's stay with the familiar
situation for a little bit one of six
children right six children yeah how did
you negotiate your way through that
competing maybe for the love and
attention of your parents maybe no um
like I said because we were given a lot
of responsibility I felt like a
co-parent early and also because
fortunately um I got the gratification
of being recognized as a a good
reader and then a good student early on
I felt like I
like
um I like being I like I like the
respect I like the respect that comes
with positions of
responsibility and being known as
someone who who can use their their
their head um even in my estate in our
you know I grew up in the council estate
in our neighborhood I was kind of known
to
be
um
uh a thinker you know someone who
someone who like
to I would say an intellectual I guess
intellectual is a wrong word but for
example when I was younger there was a
wave of uh reversion they would say to
Islam among our demographic the GU a
little older than us okay a lot of them
found Islam in the in prison to be
honest and um they came back to the
community and uh wanted to really share
what they' learned and was were sincere
about the power of Islam to improve your
life and but I was really into the
church so as a 13-year-old I used to
debate these guys who were 1920 whatever
we used to debate education education we
used to debate about spirituality all
day and they again they gave me respect
because of that they liked that about me
and the kids my age knew that my
frequency tended to I I tended towards
deep convers deep conversation I don't
know I don't know if that's how they
remember me but I remember people
recognizing like for example when I got
into Cambridge no one was surprised in
my neighborhood right yeah but again the
these are things that I liked because um
partly yeah partly because as as one of
the oldest
kids um I didn't want to ask anything of
my little siblings that I wasn't
demonstrating myself and I wanted them
to be serious about their education I
felt like our education is very um
important we weren't born into
money um and our parents made it very
clear that you know this is it like this
is how you um strategize and live your
life on your own terms you you have to
engage my mom always used to say no one
can take your education away from you no
matter what happens and I believe that I
did believe that and again the
gratification of people recognizing my
intellectual um ability
young became something that
I it was easier for me to just lean into
that and keep developing that than to
downplay myself or pretend that this
isn't what I want it's an extraordinary
story because well you hear a lot of the
time that young black men are either
objectified sexually or seen as violent
or seen as you know a number of negative
things not necessarily as an
intellectual who's on his way to
Cambridge and when he gets there it's
not a surprise so that's extraordinary I
I do want to touch on a little bit about
I was surprised they were you were ah
tell me why you were surprised all right
so I went to a grammar school which was
removed from my community like an hour
and a half away right 12 13 miles away
and um the caliber of Education was very
high um I was one of only nine black
kids out of 180 in our Academic Year so
it was predominantly Asian and and um
yeah like I said very competitive so
uh there were people who had
consistently performed better than me
throughout our school lives that didn't
make it into
Cambridge and um when I applied black
people you're saying or no not even
black people the one black kid that I
knew who also applied got in but he was
one of the the greatest students I've
ever seen in my life okay yeah that guy
was different okay
um as you are actually
no different I I I I feel like I've um
you know I've worked through a lot of
this impostor syndrome now but back then
I knew myself I I I wasn't I didn't love
the
academic method not not the method the
environment the culture of school the
kind of school I went to conservative
grammar school um I feel like it was um
it
the the the cultural dissonance was a
big drain on my education life and my
school life just not feeling the way you
know the energy of the
institution it's just like I I would
love to learn we can talk about this all
day but if I have to dress a certain way
and move a certain way and talk at a
certain time and not talk like this now
you're just you're getting in the way of
me wanting to learn now I don't want to
be here
I I kind of hear you what you're saying
about the cultural dissonance and
there's also as well the cognitive
dissonance the impact it has on your
mind the impostor syndrome that you were
having to negotiate and deal with as you
say tell us a bit more about that
because you get black students at
Cambridge at Oxford at University who
say that they get there and they feel
like they don't belong and it takes
something from them to be able to get
past the first year get past the final
year get The Graduate jobs um you know
and all of that that they have to
contend with tell me how how you managed
the the impostor syndrome as you put it
uh so when I got here I became a recluse
okay for the first time in my life
really um I wanted to be away from
people more than I wanted to be among
people right for the first time in my
life and part of that was to do with not
feeling like I uh I had the the Social
Circle that I was used to um I don't
feel that anyone was mean to me I don't
feel like it was an unpleasant
experience
I just uh ended
up becoming someone who was fully
immersed in study and as a result needed
a creative expression out of it which is
how the Poetry was born ah right okay I
became a poet here is that something you
would Advocate to black students
entering higher education and
particularly uh Elite institutions
firstly to become a recluse or would you
be advocating something else I don't
recommend it like it didn't happen on
purpose and I tried I myself challenging
I threw myself into the social scene
here at first but
[Music]
um I don't feel like I was getting as
much out as I was putting
in um I would say yeah from a from a
cultural perspective I was happy to um
go to like the four malls um these
parties that they have within or dinners
I should say that they have within
colleges and um you know we drink wine
and whatever and I'm meeting people and
I'm very very interested in everyone I
am but uh there's just such a a gap
between what I'm into and what most
people are into you know no one knows
any of the music and music was a big
thing in our lives like I said rap
became a main character no one knows any
of the music that I'm into no one really
knows the references that I grew up on
and you know like I have been in the
black community I grew up in the black
community you know from birth uh and I
was aware that there were different
communities because I spent seven years
in a school which was very
diverse um but I guess in school I still
had the option of going home at the end
of the day and um it was yeah people
there were enough people around me in
school who understood my cultural
context and um here I didn't get I was
starved of that for um a while I feel
like
I I can't speak on behalf of of students
that are here now but when I meet
students here now I just think you I
just met a couple earlier today man the
the leaders of the ACs I think just from
the little interaction I wish we were
here at the same
time I I can tell like we would have had
a um the kind of connection that I
needed when I was when I was here well
like Simon said that things have changed
certainly since the 10 years that you
are you were here what I'm hearing you
say though a little bit like Simon also
as well is that you've learned to
negotiate your way through situations in
which you aren't normally used to to a
climatize because you know you're in a
to some extent a foreign situation when
you're here when you're in private
school that you're in was there some of
that for you having to learn how to
climatize become part of the system so
to speak and learn that I mean you know
I'm not well and in your own upbringing
you're not going to formal dinners and
drinking wine as you say on a regular
basis I mean you know uh yeah there was
a lot of acclimatizing ation um when I
got here I quickly realized I was the
only black man in my year on um in my in
my college and um I couldn't really see
another black man in any of my lectures
so maybe the only one in my um faculty
in that year
again um and that didn't intimidate me
that didn't put me off I was like all
right cool let's let's you know so what
that's okay
like
let's let's learn let's have
fun um and part of that was me
performing at um talent show the month
that I got here my friend was the head
of the ACs at the time the one that I
said was the best student ever that guy
um he he got here the year before me he
was ACS president he was putting on a
show um called culture Fest 2010 and um
he wanted me to he knew me as a rapper
so he wanted me to perform right um but
again I I've already read the room I've
done my scan and I'm like I'm the only
black man on campus I'm the only black
man in my lectures I'm not going to be
known as a rapper as well that's that
doesn't feel
right especially the kind of rap that I
come from it was Grime it was the first
wave of grime is a very much Urban and I
mean urban in a geographic sense Urban
um phenomenon among our demographic and
if you weren't there I don't want to be
the first one to try and explain it to
you so
so reflecting now I um I find that
interesting you know I I I listen to it
I think about that in the way that you
might observe it as um what would you
call yourself a therapist or a yeah
therapist is good like a therapist
counselor so I put myself on the couch
I'm like what what would have been so
bad about being the representative of
your local culture in this environment
that's a very good
question right and
um I don't know I don't know it just
made the thought of it made me
uncomfortable I okay I I couldn't
guarantee that the respect was there I
couldn't guarantee that that this new
audience wouldn't be looking at me with
a bit of
a snare like uh like look what the um
look what the black gu is doing how did
it go and by the way what what name did
you use then did you have a name for
yourself at that point I just called
myself um no George the poet came like
maybe uh six six months or so into that
Journey but at the time I you know like
charin
monks like yeah I was very much into the
r rap group wuang and they were all into
um charin stuff so I took my name was an
adaptation of the word charin but it's
showering which is just a play on some
slang that we had at the time to at the
time shower
was related to sister no over there um
related to some Street stuff basically
but yeah okay yeah how did that go
anyway in the end that event yeah so um
I I said to my friend yo I'm going to
I'll perform but I'll would try it
differently I would make it a bit more
acoustic a bit more stripped back
because the Way That We R wrapped was
very percussive there was a lot of drums
there's a lot
of noise and um I thought that might be
an alienating factor to an audience who
would otherwise be open-minded if I
could present myself as more of a
communicator than an act than a than a
an an an entertainer from a different
world something exotic no I'm just a guy
talking so it might rhyme it might you
know flow if it does then all good that
was my New Concept of how I'm going to
present myself and that literally became
the foundation of everything I've done
since indeed it has indeed it has I'm
I'm very interested in the possibility
of you reciting some of that now if
you're able to yeah sure sure sure um
this is a poem called mixed messages
which is also inspired by Reflections on
Race I'm the living future of my
ancestors I'm the last chapter of the
the story that they
wrote I wish I could hear that story
from their
perspective just curious you
know I'm
conflicted CU things have changed in
ways no one
predicted I want my message to be
unrestricted but I feel like it's
becoming
scripted we want to pay homage we want
to give credit but that's symbolic
we need
systemic it's a mixed message is it us
that's
bugging how can black lives matter if
Justice
doesn't now our economics and our
politics are tied up in the West's
control in hand and we ask ourselves how
we got in this position but the answer
is simple the road was planned we
discussed the you know great black
Britains but not the colonized and
enslaved Africans whose Blood Sweat and
Tears helped to turn Great Britain into
a global
brand so how do we discuss this with our
young people if it makes the country
feel
uncomfortable mixed
messages
thank I love that I have to say um
if it makes the country feel
uncomfortable have you found that that's
what you've had to do to well one get
along and survive but also as well to be
that
educator that Communicator yeah I think
my life has just happened to fall on the
fault lines between communities a lot of
the time because of the where I went to
school studying over here um so when I
uh listened to your conversation with
Simon
it is
um Sim is such a um an accomplished
individual number one and then someone
who is so you know gen genuinely rooted
in the word that use
activism uh from such a um
substantial um vantage point you know
what you've chosen to do with your life
is uh deeply
meaningful and even
you uh have that reflex of situating
your personal experience within the
global and historical context I
appreciated what you said about um
soaking up um political Consciousness
from the barber shop I also spent many
years in the barber shop uh I was an
assistant or like a just I made myself
an assistant I used to hang out there
and um get tips for doing whatever
people wanted picking up uh food orders
sweeping up the floor whatever MH and I
I I mentioned I referenced in my work
quite a bit how rusta Consciousness was
a big part of me conceptualizing
Blackness and deciding where I fit
Malcolm X being also a hero and me just
being drawn to a strong
uncompromising political analyses of the
black condition and Men you know going
back to my role as the second child or
the you know second of six uh leading
men who don't sh leadership or or feel
that uh you know
society's putting too much pressure on
them by expecting them to answer for
their Community or or or represent I
liked people that didn't Sher that
responsibility that didn't feel like it
was improper how do you handle that
pressure because it is a pressure so I
grew
up yearning for people that didn't run
away from it
MH now I feel like
like I said I don't want to ask anything
of my younger siblings that I'm not
ready to demonstrate to impute to embody
so even though I so I I believe that
uh there won't be an individual who
improves anything you know there will
be waves of Consciousness across
Generations that shift
society that change that Rectify
Injustice wave of Consciousness so that
means it needs to be there needs to be
group reflection there needs to be group
transformation um and in advocating for
that I have to demonstrate what I'm
talking about so it doesn't feel like an
extra piece of work to think about my
responsibility to uh my community to uh
constantly demonstrate things for a
younger audience that allow them to na
navigate some of the mindfields the
cultural mindfields the intellectual
mindfields that I felt that I had to
navigate to get here and then I had to
navigate while I was here in Cambridge
wow now that's a lot I mean I don't know
where I read it but it's like you know
if a black man wants to become a leader
or an intellectual or someone that helps
the rest of the population the black
population to make make something of
themselves they have to be prepared to
put themselves through the sorts of
pressure that you're talking about and
they also as well risk being
scared off killed off bought off
something happening to them how do you
manage I'm asking you again that
pressure that risk or is it something
you just don't think about I you just
have to love it love it I love it I'm
dead serious I love it I I comedian Cat
Williams once was telling a joke
about a guy who got mored by a tiger in
a zoo in a zoo okay that's that's the
funny part part that he makes fun of and
um he talks about how everyone went on
TV and in his words snitched on the
tiger he said this is uncharacteristic
this is I can't believe the tiger did
this oh we're going to discipline this
tiger we going to put this tiger down
and um he landed the joke on the point
that the one thing someone who means it
you know the Tiger in this sense the
tiger is really a tiger and you've got
them in this playground and the one
thing that tiger wants is for anyone
someone anyone to come in this
pit and see if they're really a
tiger and he said if you can't
understand how a tiger feels in the zoo
you'll never understand how a black man
feels in
America um again I watched that when I
was young but I remember feeling like
that's a very interesting analogy and
the older I get the more I'm like
um
uh I have to constantly uh challenge
myself and challenge the people around
me to um remind you know to remember
what the point is in me being George the
poet some people get used to the easy
parts of it oh people you know um like
your uh work oh someone at my workplace
wants to take a selfie with you you know
the celebrity of it people get um
enamored with but what led me to wanting
to be uh someone who speaks about the
black condition is struggle pain uh uh
Injustice things that never should have
happened there there shouldn't exist a
museum about the enslavement of Africans
But Here we are now we don't have the
space to deal with that uh
so when when when uh someone is in the
public space with the opportunity to
speak to the consequences of everything
that's happened uh that
person cannot now get distracted with
celebrity or get distracted with um uh
riches and and F and uh you know
accolades you have to remember that uh
you
are dealing with a a gross a
disgustingly uh um unfair situation you
know we have we most of us black people
in this room have ancestors whose labor
was wiped off the
books you know were
working for something for a long time
without the accumulation of wealth
without the recognition within our
economic system of what they contributed
so uh you know after a while it feels
like generation after generation we're
starting from scratch
economically uh culturally
intellectually again the the
intellectual deficit that is
manufactured that's imposed on us we
come from cultures with Rich
histories um my wife always tells the
story we're both from Uganda when she
was a kid in Uganda once she she got a
rash her her grandma went out into the
garden ground up some leaves um made a
paste out of it put it on her rash
uh it seared off the the um the rash and
the her skin went dark but ever since
that day she's like never had a rash
again Grandma's no longer here but she
can't even uh no one even knows the uh
leaves that she uh ground up and where
she got that information from D so
there's all sorts of deficit across
black life spiritual deficit when the
missionaries came to Uganda they built
churches on top of our um spiritual
sites you know as part of the whole SC
up you know like changing us so there's
a lot that I feel the responsibility
to
represent uh and yeah that's very
important very interesting we literally
got just um a little over five minutes
left but I I do want to put this to you
um as again I said when you sat in the
chair that sometimes what we do with
counseling and Psychotherapy is we try
and think about discuss reflect upon the
relationship ship with the significant
others particularly the parents what
you're saying to me now also as well in
a way I think is that to you or to black
people in the diaspora um and in Africa
is that Africa is also as well a parent
and there is the relationship with the
parent that has either
been interrupted arrested that may have
made things be the way that they are now
but there is something about the
reconnection using the example you just
gave of your wife that might help to
make things different am I hearing this
from you I mean I know that there is a
lot of work recently that you've been
focusing on looking at in relation to
the Congo say and Patrice lumuma which
has been fascinating to read actually is
there that connection for you is there
um yeah something about the emancipation
of black people across the world that is
connected that's a very good read uh
what your your read of my um thoughts is
is on point uh I do believe that uh
there is
a
there is a reconnection that we need to
be intentional about as black people um
I I worry
about the the ease like we are in many
ways
bribed into being quiet and just going
along with whatever personal benefits we
can secure for ourselves due to
especially in the diaspora due to our
proximity to um whiteness and to White
wealth white Capital the opportunity to
uh you know get involved in
um uh Western
economies um that keeps us rooted over
here it's it's not most people's I don't
think it's most black people's intention
to leave this country in this country
you know um I think the harsher things
get the more people are considering it
and seeing the benefits of uh reiden in
with the mother the mother countries the
motherland um but uh yeah so much of our
our lives uh would just be more
convenient if we just uh go along with
the flow and we got to be mindful of
that
yeah I'm afraid we fast run out of time
but I I would hope most certainly they'd
be able to express a little bit moral um
of this in the question and answer
session but for now George the P thank
you very much for spending some time
with me
than back up few
minutes okay um it's time for a break uh
so we've got about 20 minutes um for
those of you that are online please
don't disappear when we come back we
have our final very special guest Jason
AR the youngest black male professor in
the country I think is the title that's
been given to you so looking forward
very much to talking to you afterwards
so a break now for around 20 minutes and
we'll be back with you then thank you
very much
[Applause]
everyone that is normally the most
interesting part of
the joined us online if you can send
your questions in Via slido please if
you can put your name next to your
question and then we'll try our level
best to um answer as many of those as
possible um so I'll be inviting our
guests back on but before we do that
let's um have a chat with our our final
guests so I'd like to um please invite
Jason AR onto the
stage
welcome please take a seat uh Jason and
um somebody corrected me actually when I
was uh in the Break
um the cambridge's youngest black
professor or cambridge's youngest
Professor I think probably cambridge's
youngest Professor wow okay yeah that's
really saying
something okay thank you thank you so
much uh Jason really appreciate that
you've um agreed to be one of my my
guests tonight um sometimes um um when I
start with brand new clients um I asked
them to free associate um so just say
the first thing that comes to mind
there's a game sometimes I play with
them as well I've got these cards here
which belong to my daughter who's in the
audience and they're cards with pictures
on and a single word I shuffle them and
I ask the client to take one and then
just to say something about that and
then we just continue conversation from
there so I'm going to do that with you I
hope that's okay that's brilliant okay
let's take one of those okay good
evening everyone you're well good it's
really good toone so what you got we
have nature nature okay what comes up
for you when you um see that um what
comes up nature um Greenery people um
how wonderful and beautiful this world
actually is when you're in the Stillness
of Silence the world at night um I love
nighttime and how still everything is
and then the kind of chaotic nature of
what happens in the day is So Different
At Night there's a Stillness in night
that I've always loved and that's
probably because I've spent most of my
adult life as an insomniac so I'm always
awake at night so when I think of nature
I very much think of it in the night
sense um and just how beautiful and
melodic the night sky is indeed indeed
what can you tell us about insomnia and
how that's affected you um I mean
part of it is um I spend you just spend
a lot of time thinking you think you
think you think you think and I never
had a vehicle to channel that energy
into anything useful so I would either
go running or I would teach myself how
sociology and study as much as I could
so I always found an effective way to
use that time and also um in more
difficult
times um I I had I had a job not not
that long ago really um nearly eight
years
ago um stacking shelves at SSB is and I
had a cleaning job in the day and I
would lecture um sorry a cleaning job in
the morning then I'd lecture in the day
so those were more difficult times um
because you're trying to do the best you
can to support you know friends family
and um it was a privilege doing all
those things I I learned a lot about
people I learned a lot about myself and
um I was always able at least from 21
years up to upwards to to put the night
to good use and um and tonight finds me
here indeed thank you very much again
for for being here um and good to hear
also as well that you're able
to think about doing something creative
with the time at night that you're not
able to sleep because lots of people
will just be there ruminating and
worrying and causing themselves problems
but you were able to think and do
differently in that respect yeah no um I
mean part of it as well was that um if
I'm being honest I always had this idea
that I have very limited ability and
very limited capabilities and while I
didn't have the skill um I had the will
and I needed to utilize every second and
extract every senu in my fiber to make
the best of the situation and I felt
that I needed to alucino in Any Given
Sunday talks about life being this game
of inches uh game of game of inches
right and for me it was about taking all
of those inches all of those centimeters
all those millimeters every single thing
I could take to try and maximize it and
maximize the best of what was a pretty
modest fessel so that was really part of
what I tried to do and um yeah I guess
in some respects it's led me to being
able to share and evening these
wonderful people and obviously s and
George and your good s so well and it's
brought you here but it's extraordinary
because to me it sounds like hard work
no it was really hard um I mean it
sounds like an obvious thing to say but
um it was really hard and I think that
maybe my age doesn't always betray that
um but it was really hard and you know I
guess people identify with a couple of
key ages so you know 3 11 18 and and 37
but there's a lot of things that
happened in between which is for another
time um and it was hard it was really
hard but um as my mom always said never
pray for an easy life um and it's and
and it's been a blessing having those
lessons and those
experiences um and you know there's a
perverse love of it because you learn so
much being in that state of difficulty
in that state of flux you know you find
almost this kind of Rhythm not a Cadian
when I was i' be able to sleep but you
you find a rhythm of some sort um and
you're able to kind of find find your
way into the light um and and that
becomes really important so it does so
you gave us well those ages uh can you
remember all the way back to three what
was going on for you then and what was
so significant about that age no no I
have no idea what was going on at three
it's just I I was diagnosed um with
global development delay in autism when
I was three so that that's why it
becomes a key age and then obviously as
you Traverse kind
of um childhood you you you know for me
I I I didn't speak until I was 11 so
there's a paralysis of speech in that
sense but um there was an absolute
Beauty about observing human
beings and observing the world around
you and so when you kind of draw a card
like nature that's part of it you're
observing human interaction and how you
know something as simple as touch you
know and the impact that can have on
someone and how people engage or how a
look can kind of reduce someone to tears
or how it can provide this sense of
euphoria and for me it was all
melancholic it was it was a Melody to it
which always chimed with me and there
was a chorus that was reverberating you
know as a child and if anything it it
came to an abrupt hole to be honest with
you when I learn how to speak right you
like to talk a little bit more about
before the age of 11 when you weren't
speaking out to the world I I'd like to
know about internal conversations then
what were they like or what was there an
internal conversation it wasn't really
an internal um dialogue it was more um
it was more an observation of what's
going on around you and you know a huge
part of that observation is just my
belief that human
beings are great and wonderful people
and capable of great and wonderful
things and that was an inherent belief
been instilled in me at a young age and
I guess seldom do people get to um
observe the world in situ um without the
with the absence without without the
absence of speech very few people get to
do that apart from when you're a baby
and even then there's a dialogue there a
there's some sort of connect connective
dialogue but for me I got to observe the
world and you develop these unique
perspectives on on people and you you're
able to read people um and probably more
importantly because the only thing you
can trust is
that you trust your judgment in people
and my my judgment always is is that
everybody has the capacity to be good
and some people embody that and
interweave that in every single thing
they
do a lot of people have the potential to
do it and don't do it but fundamentally
all of those things I experience as a
child taught me that nobody is born
inherently bad and there are
circumstances that may make people good
and there are circumstances that make
people bad but no one's born bad so
everyone has that Gene in them to really
tap
into engaging with that capacity to be
great to love to show compassion to show
empathy to embrace someone and make
someone feel you know and I think the
absence of
feeling pretty much surmounts to being
dead right and I mean that
metaphorically so it's this idea of
feeling and what that embodies and how
people feel it you know in here and
there's a reason why when people talk
you're moved you know George you know is
an amazing orator as is as is
Simon and there's a reason why when they
speak you know they they stir something
in people you know I've I've been
fortunate know some for a very long time
um you know George it's a really surreal
thing you know you listen listen to
someone you know thousands of times and
then here you are sat on a stage you
know potentially breaking bread with
with these people that you very much
look up to um and I guess part of that
as well um is that I had the privilege I
I I I I have a wonderful mother so I
don't call my m mom my name's gifty and
I call her GIF and every garan woman's
called gifty So like um like my mom's no
different and
um and
you know there's a funny story here and
it's I'll just keep it brief my my mom
you know she always used to say you know
God like I can't stand men like please
if you bless me with children don't
bless me with any boys don't give me any
boys and she end up with four
boys and and she always said she said
you know what like I may have had four
boys but I'm going to bring you up like
black women and and and part and part of
that is quite powerful because when
you're brought up by a black feminist
it's it's no I don't think it's a
coincidence I ended up doing what I did
for a living even though I had no idea
what I was going to do as a child so
those things become really powerful and
if anything um what my mom was an ed to
was tradition of of black women who had
uplifted and made space for black men to
thrive and I guess what's really
interesting with that as a dialogue is
that seldom do black men acknowledge
that and and I think that's really it's
an important thing for me because um all
of my practice and the way I think about
the world has very much been steered by
a black feminist way of thinking um
which which has been integral to not
only the research I do and the things
that I've done but the my way of
understanding and my way of
being it's very very interesting now
that you the first card you pick out is
nature but then there's a nature nurture
debate and how much you be socialized
into a particular position now you're
saying that no one is born bad but you
were socialized into that way of being
now a social scientist would say that
obviously they would but I guess what
I'm interested in is a little bit more
information about your your
socialization up until the time that you
were able to speak to communicate with
with others you were having some kind of
an internal dialogue tell me about the
age of 11 when you were able to then
start communicating with others what was
that like for you I mean yeah so it was
a really interesting experience so I was
I was born deaf in one ear so because I
think I'm too cool for school and I'm
not I actually have a hearing aid I'm
supposed to use which I never use apart
from when I'm lecturing so very often so
as a child um I I was signed to a lot so
I I I learned sign language or I was
taught sign language as a child and to
just kind of give you a brief scope I
spent what I would would amount to about
thousands of hours in speech therapy so
I'm the age of two to 11: I spent all I
I spent probably 10 hours a day in
speech therapy so was a long time from
2: to 11: and actually the time the
total amount of time was from 2: to
15 and so you go to these kind of
sessions you do funic excises you kind
of go through this algorithm of ways to
speak and ways to engage and um one
particular day I had this cumbersome
kind of hearing aid in my ear and we go
through the phonic exercises and I I I
take my hearing aid out
and and I and I say to the um speech
therapist who is a woman called olwin
Donnelly I forgot that name because the
only OLN I ever knew and she says Jason
how are you today and I take my hearing
aid out and I say hello now it's quite a
surreal thing when you're 11 years of
age but that's the first I didn't even
know what my voice sounded like so this
is what comes out and it's quite funny
because I got three brothers who don't
sound anything like me
so and my mom's like what did you say
like gift what gift gift like what did
you say and she I was like hello she's
she like shaking little Jason she's like
oh my God he she like God
oh she was like he heard my prayer he
heard my prayer you heard my prayer say
something else hello she was like what
do you want for dinner hello
like Jason are you feeling good hello so
obviously but at that point we're
cooking with gas and and something is
happening and then subsequently you
begin to vine the voice but I guess what
emerges when you come out of that kind
of embryonic melancholic bubble is is
you begin to understand what people are
saying um and it becomes a lexicon for
understanding what good means and what
bad means and that's where you almost
lose this vinity um this innocence in
some respects in terms of you know you
do then realize human beings can be
quite Wicked and human beings can mock
what they don't understand um but what
is interesting is that
um what my mom what GIF was able to do
and and my dad but particularly GIF was
to was to engar a really strong sense of
identity so I know Simon doesn't like
rock music but I love rock
music and it's my favorite gen of music
and you know for me one of things that
was um really powerful is that I always
had a strong sense of who I was so I was
a black kid I grew up on a council state
from South
London I was obsessed with rock
music and I was obsessed with tailoring
there are two thing the only two things
that matter to me um
and you know I remember my dad went to
this car boot sale and um he had these
two massive pictures and he just used to
buy lots of random things and just stick
them up in in the house you he said he
makes us look like we're cultured like
um and so I said to him who who who are
these two people and he said um well he
said I said cuz I said to him I'm going
to dress like that when I'm
older and he said well this person they
call him the mod father this person is a
guy called Paul well and this person is
fellow G um this is oswal boting and I
and I and I said to him like these two
look incredible he said well if you if
you want to dress like that you're going
to you're going to need to get a job
that gives you a lot of money Jason
because like it cost a lot to look like
that and you know lots of people have
lots of different dreams about the
things they want to do genuinely besides
looking after my family and friends my
only dream was I wanted to have a shirt
made on
Tavo from the age of 14 and that was the
only thing I wanted to do in life and it
was from a particular shop Huntsman so
the two oldest shops on saval row are
Henry
Paul and Huntsman um both of which have
been there for over a century and the
only thing I wanted to do was have a
tailored shirt made at Huntsman and uh
by the grace of God that that happened a
few years ago so that was that was the
only thing I ever wanted and so it's
amazing kind of you know some people
want to be rich some people want to have
a big house I just wanted to just tail
it out was my thing and I was like you
know I'm not going to be good at
anything else but I'm going to be I'm
going to be I'm going to dress the best
I mean I look like a hot mess today but
um but um but that that was my thing and
that that sense of identity was really
wielded in this idea that I know who I
am and to be honest with you my mom
fostered this idea of make sure you like
what you see because you're going to be
in states of turbulence and the one
thing you want to always be able to come
back to is this idea this strength of
identity so that was the thing that I
always came back to to and I always you
know it was and it was mapped against
this strong sense of black identity and
it was more importantly mapped against
this sense of I know who I am I'm very
interested in in this way that you've
developed yourself or nurtured yourself
as opposed to Nature based on what it is
that you've seen now you've seen these
two men uh batang and um Paul Paul well
who have influenced your love for music
or Rock but also as well dressed as well
and these are two men who were certainly
of the light guys of the time and still
have an influence today and make you who
you are today tell me about other other
men in your life that may well have had
such an influence yeah so I mean there's
probably an an obvious person that is
not admitted from this but Nelson
Mandela you know had a huge impact on my
way of thinking and it wasn't there's
there's a really important thing about
Nelson Mandela there's a romanization of
Mandela
medba and um this is this is a funny
story but it's a true story right so so
me and my brothers are all waxing
lyrical and we're like Manda you know
like Mandela like you know we we're
loving it we're talking and you know my
mom sat there twitching GIF is twitching
she's
kind like you're right GIF she like and
to give you a scope of GIF I don't know
if anyone remembers Police
Academy but my mom is the black woman
with a small voice in Police Academy but
with a garan accent so just keep that in
mind right and if you're too young to
not police cemas look it up and you'll
that's my mom and she looks exactly like
her and she's so she she's she's kind of
itching and she's twitching chomping at
a bit it's like if you're right she's
like um can I can I ask your boy
something and she's like yeah she was
like how long was n Mandela in prison
for like you Joseph chips in 27 Jose is
one of my brothers 27 years five years
under house arrest she's like okay okay
she said when you go to prison what's
the thing that gets what's the thing you
lose Simon chips in Freedom your
Liberties what I guess and then she's
like okay um like do do you know where
Robin island is yeah what is Robin
Island it's a remote island what was it
it was the most most hostile prison in
South Africa and is in the middle of
literally in the middle of South African
ocean it's like right okay
so Nelson doesn't have no Liberties he
doesn't have no freedom and he's in the
middle of the ocean an isolated island
in South Africa
who do you think was liberating a
country for 27 years whilst he was
behind
bars boys all go
quiet all we all look
down and then and go pipes up and he's
like
winie sorry what was what was that what
was that Winnie and and then I piping
zinu and she's like right and what she
was kind of the point she was making was
that there's this
romantizm figures that is often driven
by black female Endeavor and actually
what history has done is often
erode that contribution which is a lot
more significant generally speaking if
we're being absolutely candid and honest
than the contribution of black men so
the point my mom ended with is
that with black men what they don't seem
to always understand in men generally
speaking is is that um a man without a
neck is pretty headless head's flopping
all over the place and what black women
have always done is beat the neck behind
a black man and it's really important
that that isn't omitted from history and
in all of the things that we do and I
guess that that lesson was an
interesting one but it was at the catch
point I was just it was just after I
turned 16 it was it was early enough it
was late enough for me not to make the
mistakes going into adulthood that maybe
many other men have made in terms of how
we think about black women and their
contribution to the black male Endeavor
and it and it was and I was also old
enough to understand because I think if
I hadn't had that episode with GIF I
think it would have been interesting the
continuation of of habits that I might
take into adulthood and potentially not
intentionally but the the kind of
violence we cause to black women more
broadly in these spaces and not just
black men men of color um white and
white people as well fascinating story
we've got less than 10 minutes left now
and there's so much I'd love to be able
to cover um and hopefully we'll be able
to draw on some of that um in the Q&A
but here you are with catapults to so
many years later at least 25 years of
time communicating now with with with
people and here you are you know in some
ways a very high point of your life and
hopefully not the Pinnacle I'm sure
there's much more to go given that you
are the youngest professor in the
University um so what's your view about
where you find yourself now in a place
like
Cambridge um given all that you've had
to contend with with your own life yeah
that's a it's a difficult question my my
life is very different to what it was
eight months ago very very different
months ago um in fact yes it very much
is I mean eight months ago in fact I was
um at Oxford and just um running through
my last few weeks and there was somebody
there who said oh you should meet Jason
he's a really good I met him sometime
before and I we had a conversation
literally for about an hour and you
hadn't given anyone the news that you're
going to be coming to Cambridge and we
just had a conversation and we said what
we should do is we should meet up every
month and just share notes and we
haven't spoken since then because things
really have changed for you I mean it
must have been a whirlwind so tell me as
briefly as you can how the last eight
months have been and how your life has
has changed while you been here I mean
probably e it start from February so you
go to bed one night and um
and you know you're contemporaries and
probably a lot of people in the
community know what you do and then you
wake up and you know you look at your
phone and uh literally you've got over
100 Mis calls you got over a thousand
messages W um and it's
and my my dad I remember I stayed with
my M and Dad um to because I was I care
for them so I stayed with them that
particular night and my dad my dad came
in he was
like
Jason and I was like what he was like I
came to this country 40 years ago the
chef's son who'd go on to become press
like this is my victory he was like and
he's
like cuz I so to give you some cont I
hadn't told him ah so I got I got the
job in November right and there was four
and a half months where I there was only
two people on this planet who knew um
my my mom my mom and my best friend
Chantel um and sorry and two other
people one of my brothers and and a
friend so there wasn't many people who
knew can I ask what that was about why
you held back um one because I I you
know what's really interesting is that
um having been having spent most of my
my life losing to
win I'm always very was that time having
spent most of my life losing to win
losing to win losing to win yes so there
was a line from a Cassian song called
Underdog and um I always I always
understood how important it was to lose
with good grace and I always empathized
with the person who was on the other end
of the result okay
so the people that also applied for the
job a lot of my thinking was they will
feel a huge sense of disappointment okay
and part of keeping it to myself is
because apart from anything else that
there is a humility that one must sit in
in recognizing that you've been yes
you've worked hard but you've been
fortunate there are people particularly
black and ethnic minority people
particularly black people actually who
are just as able if not more capable and
more deserving and for some reason you
know my fate laid in the lap of the Gods
and and they they smiled upon me so the
least you can do with that Grace is is
to sit in humility um um and that's what
I tried to do um and obviously my dad
coming in saying it was his victory and
it's all down to him um you you let him
have his moment but then you also kind
of think how surreal it must be for
someone coming to what is effectively a
pretty hostile country
for you know for people from
particularly people from immigrant
populations and the idea that you know
he could never have foreen this
potentially happening and so for me it
was a pretty surreal thing
because I remember I remember I stayed
at home for the first day and then the
next day I came out and I must have been
stopped
by I'm not even I'm not Jo exaggerating
I must have been stopped by over 500
people on the way from home to on the
way from home to wherever I was going to
wow and they were just like just thank
you for everything you've done it's
you're not a footballer you're not a
rapper you're not a you know so and all
the they just listened all these like
you're ours and what you've done is a
reflection on all of us and just and you
didn't I didn't realize how much it
meant to
everyone um and as my friends all joke
you couldn't meet a more
reluctant star because the only thing I
ever wanted was a tailored shirt from
some so um but but but with that
um the thing that you kind of take away
from that
is so I don't believe in impostor
syndrome you don't and I don't believe
in imposter syndrome
because faith is I walk in faith and
what do you mean by that my faith is a
huge part of of who I am so I believe
that God places people where they're
supposed to be and I believe that for
everybody so there's never anything that
comes in mind my mind that I don't know
if I belong here or not I I think I was
destined to be here right um can I ask
you this then that having that faith and
that way of responding to the situation
which you find yourself in helps you to
manage the let me put this way the
burden because this is a huge burden a
huge 500 people on the way to work stop
you the first day after you've announced
that you're going to be a professor and
you manage that very gracefully and is
that because you have the faith and the
belief that's helped you to to manage
what is a huge pressure and burden yeah
I I I think that's a part of it I think
a part of it is temperament okay
um I think I've been very fortunate that
I think I've been blessed with quite a
good temperament so you know I probably
don't get too high and I don't get too
low I try and stay in the middle but I'm
also not made of stone you know there is
a very difficult side to it and you you
know restraint is a very underrated
quality it's very underrated quality
when particularly in the face of
absolute
provocation racial provocation to be
specific
um to to demonstrate restraint um the
faith becomes an important thing because
what my faith teaches me is to try and
show compassion and forgiveness and so I
come across people who say the most vile
and wicked of
things but I I have the are you able to
say what sorts of things in the last
couple of minutes right to say do you
know what I could say it but I I I don't
want to give them the oxygen because
what's more important is that
um I forgive them and and I love them
and if I if they ever came to my face
and said to me what they think I would
try and engage in the teaching episode
and I would I would I would guesstimate
they may not have been shown what love
is and Simon spoke about that kind of
proxy of love and I would take that as
an opportunity to demonstrate to them
what love looks like and that's what I
would do so um I don't have no malice I
don't wish these people know ill um but
um my my time at Cambridge will will
come to an end one day um but it won't
be at their hand it'll be at mine and
when I decide that the time is is right
and like the All Blacks Jersey you're a
custodian of the Jersey your job as an
all black is to put it in a better
condition than when you first received
it so there are some exceptional people
in the audience tonight and probably
online and some of those people will
take the charge and they will do a much
better job than I have done and then
when their time is up they'll move it on
and someone else will take it so the
capacity to love is situated in faith
and my faith teaches me that two wrongs
don't make a right so where people show
me
um hatred and they show something from
within um I see it as an
opportunity
to to strengthen my purpose
around
interweaving you know with Needle on the
thread as much as I'm able
to love into our society and and how we
engage with people and that's how I will
always be because that's how I was
brought up Amen to that jard thank you
very much for spending time with me on
theate St where you
are okay um we've got just under 30
minutes I think I'm right for Q&A so
we're just going to gather a couple of
chair up on the stage so please give us
a couple of minutes and then I'll invite
our guests back up on stage just give us
two minutes
please if you can start thinking about
what questions you might that would help
too thank you so much Paul thank
you that's
brilliant okay if I can invite um both
George and Simon back on
please
nice it's a lovely moment you
too okay thank you very much um for
coming back in okay so uh let's um open
the floor um if you could please give
your name and ask your question as
concisely as you can and who it's
directed to and we'll take it from we'll
take it from there so who'd like to ask
the first
question see a hand over
there uh so can you hear me okay yes we
can can you state your name and your
your question please so my name is y um
and my question is about for the free of
you the relationship between your
Academia and your mental health there
was a situation last week where I had a
conversation with my white counterparts
in my kitchen about Philosophy for 2 and
a half hours and I realized I was a nerd
but I liked it and I was no longer
fighting it and I real and I also
recognized that having spent time in
this institution and done my a levels
the relationship I had with Academia was
very very itic without me knowing it was
therapeutic and I guess for the three of
you um how did you found how did you
find your relationship with your in with
your intellectual developments and how
that impacted your mental health thank
you for that good question who'd like to
uh answer that one
first in some ways mine didn't come
naturally to me so I I had no
intellectual or academic Acumen
whatsoever it's just it was a case of um
you know Simon and
George they've got one hit quitters in
other words in boxing terms they can get
their opponent out on two or three
rounds whereas me I'm punch drunk I'm a
12 round fighter I've taken too many
blows to the head and um and I find it
really difficult so wouldn't cathartic
or therapeutic is not necessarily what I
would say so it's always been this this
this act of suffering because I find it
really difficult but you know the
perverse love of sufferings that you can
begin to find love for it you know and
so I wouldn't from a mental health point
of view when I became a professor um
when I was 35 at Glasgow it was almost
the suffering can come to an end you can
begin to enjoy it now and I guess I've
only really had two or three years now
beginning to think about it in a
different way and so maybe I'll be where
you are hopefully sometime soon um and
if you can think of it like that as a
cathartic thing hold on to that try to
ensure that you don't let anything
infringe upon that
because I mean this might sound like a
crazy thing to say but I I don't really
like research I find it difficult it's
being an academic is really really
difficult and I say that because
effectively I'm exploring the phenomena
of race and racism and the difficult
thing is listening to people talk about
these really painful experiences of
experiencing racism and then you've got
to encapsulate that voice and and and
you know provide something that is
legible and digestible and that's that
side of it is difficult so if you can
find the enjoyment of it try not to lose
that almost childlike enthusiasm because
it it once you lose it it's a hard thing
to get back and sometimes I think about
when I started 10 years ago and where I
am now and I've you lose the enthusiasm
because you know these painful
experiences not necessarily yeah I I've
encountered them but you you you hear
you you know when you interview over 600
people of color and they tell you all of
their experiences around racism you know
you're green when you first start you're
wet behind the ears and then your ears
begin to dry and that green turns to Red
because you become really angry about
what people are experiencing and it's
it's just it's different that's very
useful response thank you Jason let me
just ask you this then um because as a
therapist we sometimes operate as a
container for the pain that our clients
bring us but we have to find ways of
being able to to let go of that or
release that whether that's via clinical
supervision or also as well via
well-being related activity very briefly
then is there anything more that you do
to mind your own well-being in relation
to the question I was asked yeah I mean
it comes back to this idea of I always
write in my work this idea of anger
being privileged so who is allowed to
express annoyance anger upset anguish
and I guess the thing that I do which
I'm a cautionary tale it's it's nothing
to be proud of you you kind of learn to
be a robot
got
so you manage emotion you the most I
would do is put my head under a pillow
and scream and even to do that I'd make
sure there was no one in the house so
it's not it's not particularly anything
to be proud of um because you understand
that actually I have to be softly spoken
I have to have shof shoulders try not to
raise my voice try and keep my hands
below my pelvis there's so many
algorithms you have to do to engage as a
black man so you don't
be awarded the moner of being aggressive
or angry or violent so you know a lot of
the things that I do if I'm going to be
honest what I'm about to tell you is a
really silly thing but it's what I
personally do so I love home and away
and
neighbors and the is so disconnected to
my reality is I deliberately try and
engageing things that are completely cuz
I'm never going to go to Australia i'
got really no interest in these people
other than the fact that it's just so
different from what my Norm is so
everyone has the things that they do I
mean the tailoring is a big thing if I'm
being honest it's my obsession so that's
probably a big a big part of it as well
thank you thank you Jason um Simon
George do would you like to respond to
the
question
um earlier in my life uh my uh academic
career was tied up in a lot of
anxiety um the the exam cycle I found to
be quite
stressful but um the reward afterwards
when I felt like I made progress was a
big boost and I think the cumulative
reward of all of that progress became my
fundamental expectation of Academia if
you apply yourself you will
grow and um that's where I'm at now uh a
lot of my even though I'm a poet a lot
of my work now especially in the form of
my podcast is quite academic it's become
more and more um research focused as
I've pursued my
PhD um and it it's cathartic because
I'm talking about um things on a deeper
level than I ever have and because I'm
able to share this with people make it
accessible it doesn't just it's no
longer a closed loop of sitting in the
room writing an essay only to do it next
week There's an output that I think is
Meaningful and that's quite rewarding
that's BR I think I think we'll take
another question from the floor and then
we'll take uh one of those that have
come from online so who'd like to go
next you can see your hand
here if you can say your name if you
don't sorry my name is Aisha thank you
all for sharing so openly today I have a
question for each of you I'm sorry to
take some time um I suppose in you know
we look at anger as a negative thing but
essentially I think a lot of the
literature that's coming out
particularly in activist space is
essentially an anger often drives us so
my question to Simon in particular
is is there any way that you can frame
it as a positive and reflect on actually
how that's driven you to do the work
that you do and and in the trauma that
you've experienced is there any
reflection on
potentially the work that you do um
being therapeutic to you um question for
Jason so you said something quite
powerful there is you were thanked over
500 times and you were seen as a you
know you were representing a community
so on the other side of that
particularly for students that might be
in an institution like this where they
are seen as achieving something
exceptional how do you find a balance to
not overwork because of the expect
expectation that's been placed on you
just thinking about the students mental
health and one for you Georg it's a big
one here but
um particularly maybe because you've
come from that more workingclass
environment and you are seeing you know
in a space like this to have broken
almost every sort of trajectory that was
planned for you
um I guess the question is when we think
about contextualization talking to the
young black boys and young black girls
that would be listening to this podcast
and knowing how much you know especially
when you talk about affirmative action
roll backs in the US and you know
contextualization offers here and how
actually I I believe it's a good thing
but actually how do you speak to those
young black students that might be faced
with questions in terms of their
validity in being in a space like this
um and just speaking into them in a way
that you know in ASE the questions that
you definitely would have asked yourself
about your right to be here okay thank
you for those three questions um if you
can respond to those as for the as
briefly as you possibly can and Simon
I'd like to I'd like to start with you
question related to it's great it's
great channeling anger because it I
think it's okay to be angry to be
frustrated to be impatient but how you
channel that is is the gift and uh and
sometimes you'll see the fruits of your
labor tonight I'm seeing the fruits of
my labor uh I I've known George when we
started operation black vote uh obv was
25 30 years ago
and George was an upand cominging
poet and uh I'm not sure who got in
touch with who but we got in touch with
each other and he came to London and he
he would join some of our events and we
would give him a platform and he would
have this um this uh political dexterity
and
musicality and passion that just blew
everybody away I mean he wasn't well
known then and then I've seen him now
and he's a superstar and and a reluctant
super super star because it's about what
he what he does rather than his ego and
on my left Jason came to operation black
vot uh 15 or so years ago and he came to
came to me and he said Simon I want to
change the
world and I said hop on board and I
remember I remember he'd been with us
for a year and uh there was
um a a BBC interview and they wanted
somebody and I I he knows what I'm gonna
say and he was like no I can't do it
looked him in the eyes yes you can yes
you can and he he just hit the ball out
the park and then to see this young man
who was as nervous as hell uh to be the
beacon I mean that's how you turn anger
into hope into reality these two guys
and we didn't even know I didn't even
know that you were going to put us all
together um but that golden thread the
golden thread and there's another golden
thread too we're all Council house kids
we're all from the council estate
punching above our
weight Simon before I move on to George
one thing you're very brilliant at doing
also as well
is praising others and pointing to
others and their achievements and the
question was necessarily directed to you
now I remember and I think it's in your
book that when you well it certainly was
the same for me first saw the program
roots that stood up a lot of anger it
certainly did for me and look what me
and my Breen wanted to do was beat up
the first white person we saw for all
those years of slavery but we managed to
contain our anger I guess the question
is how have you managed if I'm
interpreting properly what you're saying
the all that you've come across which
would make anyone angry black or white
and still able to come to where you are
and this is a question directly for you
and how you manage that situ I mean it's
hope it's hope in humanity hope how
things how things can be and uh I think
Jason has said
look go through life thinking if I give
you at some point you'll respond well to
me and with me and uh that that having
anger into
toxicity is like a cancer really I mean
it's going to destroy you I refuse to be
destroyed that's great thank you George
you want to respond to the question that
directly would you like it repeated or
you cool how do we how how what do I say
to a young person that might struggle
with the impostor syndrome in a place
like this in the context of affirm
vacine Etc
um
um I I would say that there's first of
all intrinsic value in who you are which
um took me a while to wrap my head
around that I always thought you had to
earn the right to be heard
uh you don't however um how you address
yourself to whatever challenge you take
on if it's an academic aspiration if
it's a physical goal how you address
yourself to that um then becomes your
qualification you know did you show up
are you serious have you been consistent
are you willing to learn humble yourself
fall back pivot where possible these are
things that take adjacent from Jason you
know from not being able to speak for 10
years 11 years to um becoming
cambridge's youngest Professor uh Jason
described not being a knockout artist if
you know in a boxing analogy having to
Slug it out in terms of um you know the
nitty-gritty of Academia
and that's that's what life really is
there are people who have
um uh attained everything material but
now are going through that struggle in
their marriage or with their child um
and they they're not going to get a an
award or a trophy for whatever struggle
they go through but they will be
transformed by how they address
themselves to that challenge that's
great thank you George and the question
for you Jason would you like that repeat
it or you I sit and I've embarrassed
myself can't even
remember very briefly if you can repeat
the question again how do you not over
expect thank you so much very good
question thank you so much
[Music]
um yeah you you you you can't change the
habit of a lifetime
unfortunately this is the DNA of Jason
AR day I'm going to run it until the
wheels haul off and then I'll feel that
problem when it comes and that's what I
mean I'm the cautionary tale of you
don't become a professor the age I do if
you haven't you know there's a lot of
things Mr Miagi in karate kid says
balance makes good karate and the one
thing I've never had in my adult life is
balance and if you have balance you can
enjoy it part of the reason why I don't
always enjoy it is because I don't
actually I don't balance things very
well and so and that's me being as
honest as I could be and if you really
want to be happy if you really want to
embrace R this I don't think it's
mythical I think happiness really exists
I think balance is very important and
the cautionary tale is I've chased
Fool's Gold but if someone asked
me except for making other people happy
are you happy I would say no because
you're tired and
actually part of being in this space is
You' think you'd enjoy it but you're
tired because you've just balance is so
important and the thing I would say to
people is uh with balance as Mi Mr Miagi
says you'll have good karate Daniel son
if you don't have good balance you don't
have good karate so that's that's what I
would always say um and that's why I
know that this won't last forever it's
not everything and I know that you know
I don't want to put it in years but it
probably haven't got long left cuz if
you burn the candle that hard from the
age of 21 to 38 you're just not going to
be able you know so but a I hope that
the little I've done has Move That All
Black's Jersey on some some way great
thank you um I think I'll take a a
question from online and this came from
vcal and this one's uh for you uh Simon
how can you overcome subtle racism when
applying for senior roles now you're
you're Brilliance as I was saying
already at assisting and supporting the
black students that come to honton and
to Cambridge actually I mean it's
fantastic what you've done uh
particularly online in showing your
support for that but but you know the
question is how can you have a come
suffer races and apply for senior roles
in this country yeah I mean i' I've
thoroughly enjoyed nurturing Talent um
and uh there's two other people in the
audience from operation black vote uh
two sisters and it's just great because
honestly honestly somebody told me as a
parent as a new parent they said it's
not rocket science uh you you give you
give uh 10% with the child and you get
100% back and and actually it's not too
UND dissimilar uh when you're nurturing
when you're nurturing Talent um
but nurturing talent to to go through
barriers and and and
obstacles I honestly felt that I had to
do it myself
too to know that lived experience and
before I got this job I was head hunted
for a job in in in Oxford I won't
mention the college
unless you buy me a drink
afterwards anyway the process was six
months and about 15 interviews and I was
down to the last two when you get down
to the last two you got to think you got
to you know you got to start believing
it right I was doing the measurements in
the
house or almost and then I got the call
and said yeah you were close but and I
tell you I tell you it was like a hammer
blow and I I slumped and started to
question myself actually you know what
got me out of it when the person arrived
they said I'm coming back
home and so they'd been there and they
knew them and so you know it was an
easier option and then I thought to
myself you know what I can't win this
beauty
contest you know right now with but you
can brilliant
love that I paid him to come at right at
that
time against these young guys
too but I said I said to
myself if I'm to nurture Talent like
these women in front of us if I'm to
tell them when you get knock down you
you got to get back up brush yourself
down I said in my head I'm thinking I
can't win this beauty contest but I need
to keep trying so I can tell others and
so when homon came knocking on the door
I said okay I'm going to try one more
time I'm going to try I'm going to try
I'm going to put myself out there 6
months 6mon interview process all all
online and then I got the call you know
what they said it was
unanimous I said damn time to
work thank you thank you for that um
right I did see our hands over here so
if we can take that and then I see one
other person over there and we might
have to win then uh your name please and
then a question thank you U my name is
Tony um my question is I guess what's
listening to all of you what's the end
game as black men both individually and
Community um you've both you've all
talked about success both your Journeys
too and interpretations of but they're
very different Lord Willie talked about
putting personal pain aside to get to
success so he could have a platform to
make a difference George talked about
not kind of getting distracted by
eurocentric conceptions of success and
proximity to White Capital Etc and then
uh not to do a disservice to um to the
professor but he talked about just
wanting a tailored shirt um and has
overe exceeded um by all expectations so
as black men what should we be striving
for and how do we Define that for
ourselves it's a great question thank
you and George being the youngest on the
panel um what's the end game um I think
preparation of the Next
Generation that is that must be the end
game even if you're not going to become
a parent yourself uh it's it's it's why
Simon has such fulfillment in his work
in being here in seeing his mentees in
the audience uh the the next generation
is constantly incoming and they are
constantly in need of support beyond
what the institutions provide for them
so um I I again going back to masaki
being a big brother I
just need to know that through my own
progress at the end of this this journey
I have little brothers and sisters who
feel a little more confident in how
they're going to navigate and look at
the efforts I made to give them some
game and um they pay it forward to the
next
Generation thank you George Jason how
about you yeah I I think it goes back to
that kind of alteristic 18yar old you
know when I was 18 the most seminal
thing that happened to me is my mom took
me to a homeless shelter when I was 18
and from that experience I knew exactly
what I wanted to do besides having a
tailored chip um I I I I wanted to save
the world and it's what I said to Simon
when I met him you know several years
later and part of that was that I wanted
to raise as much money as I could for
charity and I wanted to help as many
people as possible and um by the grace
of God I've been very fortunate to be
able to to raise Millions for charity
but it's really a continuation of that
and really again it's about that All
Black's Jersey um and you know the
amazing work that Georgia has done
the amazing work that Simon has done and
others and great people like yourself as
well R me and kind of really continuing
that Legacy and that black tradition and
leaving the jersey in a better condition
than when we found it for the next
custodians to take it on board and it it
always comes back to to that to that
kind of All Blacks Mantra which I you
know and I use the All Blacks as an
Exemplar because I think they're
probably the best sporting franchise
ever one of the oldest um you know over
a century old and I think everything
that embodies that mildy culture is
something that has actually been
extracted in many respects from
indigenous culture black culture and
it's all embodied in this jersey but
it's a good metaphor for how we all look
to move things forward and you know
there's always you know it's almost like
an a relay hand Buton and it'll be
someone else's turn and you kind of
shoot off that's brilliant and and
yourself Simon I mean having being
instrumental in developing operation
black vote and getting many people to
vote in a when they would never have
done that before entering the House of
Lords as a black man and now here we are
being the principal the first black male
principal of a Oxbridge College what
more is there to do I mean I'm happy
with the life of struggle on uh I am
challenging institutions transforming
institutions I mean that that is a worth
a life worth lived but but trust me on
this one you have to have
joy you honestly please don't ignore Joy
uh for the the worthy Endeavor of
struggle you know we had Joy last week
uh we had a Black History Month dinner
and in our in our big fancy dining hall
we had
300 uh majority uh students of African
descent and as many as that here at C
there is there is there is H and um
showcased fashion icon and super sister
Naomi Campbell let me tell you let me
tell you there was so much joy in that
room so much joy of being black so much
joy of being happy together I'm thinking
to myself I could retire right now and
you know here's the thing about it is
that uh Nami Campbell hasn't always been
in places of
joyous but she was joyful on that day
and embraced it that manager wanted her
to leave she wouldn't leave because she
knew the sisters wanted a picture with
her so she had pictures with every every
one joy and the other bit of Joy I'm a
bit like my brother here you know we
work hard but we like to look
good and the sisters too don't don't see
several row shoes sow Blue Suede
Shoes in the
house you know what really funny I
remember the first time I saw s r neck I
was like he's wearing a r neck I'm going
to wear
a remember huging him oh he smells on
believe that's fantastic sounded short
by the way thank you for that thank you
for that Simon I think we've probably
got time for just one more question and
I did see a hand up over there so you
said just set it back
there yeah hi um my name is Sean and my
question is to Simon I've written down
because it's a bit loaded um but yeah um
so in your position as principal of
homon college you've been able to
accommodate people from your community
in like really hardw in commendable ways
um and obviously the dinner last week
was Testament to that um yeah shout out
cam again um yeah however I am curious
what goes through your mind and guid
your steps when your identity inevitably
comes into conflict with your position
and responsibilities to a wider
institution that obviously includes
people Beyond fascinating question it's
a great question and and uh it's
constantly I mean these two brothers
would know too it's a Highwire act that
uh first and foremost I have to be true
to
myself and once I lose that I've lost
the game I'm not I'm not worthy of being
in the
space um but I also know that to move
the dial I have to
compromise uh I have to play the game
um I'm as frustrated as hell because I
see so much potential in these
institutions you know one of the things
we talked about education and and how
important it is and the brothers so
important it is that I'm of the I'm of
the Dr Martin Luther King uh school of
thought that academic
Excellence without character of the
individual is almost worthless
L because you can take that intelligence
and get puffed up and be a
shocker an absolute
shocker that my privilege and my gift
that I'm trying to do for hon and for
Cambridge is to say I want you to have
the academic Excellence I want you to
have that that uh uh willly Wonker
golden ticket but I want more than that
I want to nurture your character so it's
not about you but about what you can do
and
about how you can take that gift and
that learning and do extraordinary
things and uh I'm in the hot seat watch
this
space okay I'm afraid uh we're out of
time um but thank you so much three of
you I mean it's fantastic that you've
come through the system here at
Cambridge and are who you are so thank
you so much uh George the poet thank you
so much uh Lord Simon woly and thank you
so much Jason lard thank you all and
thank you very much for coming everyone
thank
you right um I think we'll probably be
around for a few more for more minutes
so George's book is outside if you
wanted to purchase one I'm sure he'd be
willing to sign a copy or so if you've
got any questions that you want to ask
quite privately either of myself or
other other guest I think we'll hang
around for a few more minutes there
might still be some more Refreshments
outside so we'll be around for a few
more minutes thank you again everybody
thank you so
much that was
great